Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Do you always carry Endless Promise
on you when you go out?
Only when I come here.
Your Lordship is very filial to Her Venerable Highness.
You have Endless Longing with you.
I'm Endless Promise's owner,
on my way to see Endless Longing's owner.
Your Lordship is good at making jokes.
I'm not joking with you, Huan'er.
But I can only treat this as a joke.
You were a concubine of the emperor before.
But you are free now.
So I wasn't joking with you.
It's my true feelings.
After you left the Cooling Terrace,
I restrained myself from visiting you
because I feared that you would be hurt, or uneasy.
But do you know how sad I was?
"Banana leaves furled;
the budding lilac not bloomed."
"They stand in the spring wind
but face their own sorrows."
I don't know if you feel the same as I do.
But I'm afraid
that this has been the hardest spring
to get through of my entire life.
I was a favored concubine in the palace.
Now I'm practicing Buddhism in
the Temple of Pure Dew,
and have nothing to do with the palace anymore.
But I‘m not an emotionless stalk of grass.
I'm not unaware of how Your Lordship feels.
But in my declining years out of the palace,
I don't want any more attachment
with the imperial descendants.
You are unable to accept me
because you used to be
His Majesty's concubine,
and because I was born into the imperial family.
But when you were in the palace,
did you ever have a day of peace and happiness?
Of all our encounters in the palace,
was there ever a time that you were truly happy?
There wasn't! Even your tears had to be restrained.
Even if I never had to have lived in the palace,
the past is different from the present after all.
Whether it's now or before,
putting aside your time in the palace,
you've always been free.
You can be together with anyone you want.
You just said
that you aren't a stalk of grass.
You are not emotionless.
In some part of your heart,
you like me
at least a little bit, am I right?
I remember that day
you called me by my name.
Has Your Lordship ever been in love?
No, I haven't.
I have experienced it.
So I understand
that if you know from the beginning
that something will not end well,
it's better to avoid wishful thinking
and trying to force a good result.
Just like His Majesty and me.
If from the very beginning,
I treated him like other concubines did,
only seeking opulence and glory,
and never a shred of true love,
then I wouldn't be the one who
implicated my father.
Your heart has only been hurt once.
Are you going to give up on love because of that?
Given that I know I'll only get hurt,
I would rather never have to know him
or meet him.
If...
there was someone who would dedicate himself
to create an endless springtime in your life
and shelter you from the snow and rain.
Would you still refuse him?
"This young lady from a humble family"
"has no intention to attach herself to royalty."
The past has now become a dream,
and I can see my future as clearly
as the bottom of a lake.
So there's nothing for me to dream for any longer.
Your Lordship once said
that you don't like the Duke of Pei's daughter
despite her outstanding virtue and manners.
I feel the same about Your Lordship.
Although Your Lordship is from
the imperial family,
and closely related to the emperor,
Your Lordship happens not to be to my liking.
Our mistress hasn't smiled much since
she came back from the Cooling Terrace.
What could be the matter?
Nothing.
But she's been so quiet.
If it weren't for these birds Dr. Wen sent
a few days ago to lighten her mood,
she might be even more reserved.
What's that noise?
What is it?
Cats!
Jinxi, beat the cats away!
My Lady has been hurt by a cat before,
she's terrified of them!
My Lady.
It's all right. Huan'er. Huan'er.
Huan'er, it's safe here.
I chased the cats out.
Your Lordship...
What kind of cats are so big?
Wild mountain cats.
Why would you
keep pet birds when you live in the mountains?
There might not be huge beasts here,
but there're plenty of wild cats, which feed on birds.
Fortunately, no one got hurt.
Dr. Wen is to blame.
He sent those birds to cheer up My Lady,
but ended up attracting wild cats.
I thank Your Lordship.
If it weren't for your help,
I really don't know what would have happened.
I was so frightened.
I have never seen such big cats.
It really was because of Dr. Wen.
His good intentions led to bad results.
I'm grateful for Your Lordship's help.
But why is Your Lordship
around here so late at night?
These days you stay up until nearly midnight.
No wonder you look so haggard.
You've been here all this time?
I just wanted to wait until you were asleep.
But I was already asleep.
Why were you still here?
Huan'er,
you can think of it as me
being attracted by the moonlight.
It's all my fault for not coming sooner.
I fell into a slumber.
I'm sorry that you had a scare.
Your Lordship is as distinguished as gold.
Why would you trouble yourself like this?
This is not trouble.
It brings peace to my mind
so long as I can be outside
and see the light coming from your quarters.
Your Lordship, please go back and sleep.
It's around midnight already.
Please go to sleep with your mind at ease.
I...
I will take my leave.
Your Highness, Concubine Délice
served His Majesty again last night.
She has a good family background
and Her Majesty thinks highly of her.
It's only natural that she gains
more of His Majesty's favor.
She talks excessively and is unpleasant.
And she never lets up on Your Highness.
She's so annoying.
She looks down upon me because of
her family's contributions.
But, favor and status in the palace
are decided by family background.
They aren't.
Even I can see that His Majesty
likes Your Highness more.
What's the point of being liked?
Gaining favor is the most important.
Also, the spice from last time has run out.
Has my father had more sent here?
I've passed on the message.
They should arrive soon.
Good.
It's a shame that I am still
not able to have a child.
Her Majesty doesn't like more children
to be born in the harem.
I'm relying on her,
so I have no choice but to obey her orders.
Yes.
About Daisy, the maid.
She hasn't been serving
Your Highness all along after all.
Since she is of no use,
we don't need to keep her any longer.
Your Highness, His Majesty just
dismissed the morning court.
How about I accompany you to pay your respects?
No.
His Majesty has been busy dealing with
issues regarding Longkodo.
It would be best to refrain from visiting.
Peace to you, Imperial Mother.
Have a seat.
I haven't been visiting the Palace of Longevity recently.
Please don't blame me, Imperial Mother.
Things are busy in the imperial court.
You're right to pay more attention to it.
Although things have been busy
these days at court,
they all come down to one issue.
That is, that Longkodo has formed a faction
and undermined the authority of his sovereign.
After eliminating Nian Gengyao,
as expected, it's now Longkodo's turn.
I thought that Longkodo could retire
peacefully in his old age.
But you still won't make allowances for him.
It's not that I don't make allowances for him.
It's that he doesn't make allowances for himself.
When Nian Gengyao was alive,
they had many strong links.
You've known for a long time that Nian Gengyao
and Longkodo never got along with each other..
To maintain harmony at a superficial level,
you suggested that Longkodo should
foster Nian Gengyao's eldest son.
If you're saying that they colluded with each other,
doesn't that make you the chief plotter?
Longkodo has committed heinous crimes.
It wouldn't be unjust if I had made
a false accusation or two.
In fact, he has committed more than ten serious crimes.
Even when he descends beneath the nine hells
and defends himself to the judge of the underworld,
he still won't be able to justify his crimes.
Imperial Mother, you plotted with
me to eliminate Nian Gengyao.
But when it comes to Longkodo,
why do you try your utmost to protect him?
Is it that you feel indebted to him because of your
acquaintance with him from a young age?
I have said before
that Nian Gengyao and Longkodo
provided major support for your
accession to the throne.
Since Nian Gengyao could not be tolerated,
we should not eliminate Longkodo.
Otherwise, people will say
"After the cunning hare is killed,
the hound is boiled".
And they will accuse you of "tearing down
the bridge after crossing the river."
I'm only saying this to protect your reputation.
Anyone else I could spare,
but Longkodo must die.
Longkodo is the brother of Empress Xiaoyiren
and he is your uncle in name.
Even if you don't account for Longkodo himself,
you should at least consider
Empress Xiaoyiren's prestige.
Longkodo must be killed not only for me,
but to also protect your reputation.
Longkodo has had a close relationship
with you since childhood
and you both had affection for each other.
Just because Father wasn't aware
doesn't mean I also don't know.
What happened during the Double Third Festival?
I'm sure you know better than I do.
Imperial Mother, not only do you
have to protect Father's prestige,
but also mine.
If you can't bear to see him die,
then it means you would rather imperil the throne I strove hard for
and your honored status as Empress Dowager.
As for Longkodo,
I have already confined him in a private
chamber of the Garden of Vibrant Spring.
Imperial Mother, I hope you will
protect my prestige and reputation.
Stop! Who are you?
I am Madam Bamboo,
maid of the Empress Dowager.
I'm bringing Longkodo's family to see him.
It won't take long.
Madam Bamboo, it was foolish of me
to not have recognized you.
Please, head on in.
Please go in. I'll stay here to keep watch.
Who are you?
It's me.
The humble servant Longkodo
bows before Your Majesty.
Please stand up.
When I first met you, you were high-spirited.
But now, it has come to this.
It's all my fault.
No, it is my own fault.
Your Majesty is esteemed above all.
I'm eternally grateful that Your Majesty
would visit me, on the verge of my death.
We have known each other for many years.
I felt obliged to visit you.
It is cold and damp here.
Has your leg been all right?
I thank Your Majesty for asking.
My leg has improved a lot.
I hope Your Majesty won't mind the
unsightly furniture. Please have a seat.
Your leg was injured because you saved me.
Of course I am concerned about it.
You should sit as well.
I thank Your Majesty.
It is an honor to serve Your Majesty.
I've heard that Your Majesty has constantly
been ill after moving into the Palace of Longevity.
Although I was worried, I was unable to
visit the harem very often.
I hope Your Majesty will forgive me.
I have been taking the medicine you sent me.
But my aging body is no good anymore.
All those years ago, Noble Consort
Wenxi was domineering，
Consort Liang surpassed my favor,
and Consort Serein gained exclusive favor.
It didn't feel like much to me
after dealing with them one after another.
But now, even just thinking back to it
makes me feel exhausted.
Your Majesty is blessed by Heaven.
The past has already vanished like a fleeting cloud.
In the end, it was Your Majesty who was blessed
and became the Mother of the Nation.
That being said, I will always remember
how you supported me throughout.
From just a mere Escort to becoming
the prior emperor's Noble Lady Digne,
and all the way to Consort Digne,
and in the end, the Empress Dowager.
I will never forget the generous help you gave me.
Your Majesty, I don't deserve the credit.
Over the decades,
the one thing I always remembered was
when we met in our humble origins.
That year, on the Double Third Festival,
the third day of the third month
Your Majesty and I...
On that day, you said
that you had already made arrangements.
You told me to wear pink and blue
during the Concubine Selection
because the prior emperor didn't like those colors.
That way, I wouldn't be selected
and would be able to marry you afterward.
But who can ever foresee things in this world?
I was selected anyway and became a concubine.
Your Majesty is blessed by Heaven.
It was my fate.
There is no need to speak of fate anymore.
We have already lived the most years of our lives.
You have your wife and many concubines
and I became the Empress Dowager.
Since it was destined to be this way,
no one could have changed it.
I'm here today not only to
reminisce about the past,
but also to tell you that
I will find a way to plead to the emperor for you.
I thank Your Majesty.
Stand up.
You are an old friend of mine.
It is only right for me to help you out.
This is your favorite Bamboo Leaf Wine,
and I prepared these dishes myself in the kitchen.
I don't know if my cooking
is still the same as before after all these years.
"Getting drunk eases a thousand sorrows."
I thank Your Majesty
for preparing these dishes.
In your heart,
I am always the Empress Dowager.
You have forgotten that I'm also
Uya Chengbi, whom you have known from childhood.
No matter how the world has changed,
I will never forget that you are Chengbi.
I hope so.
You... You...
I...
I am the Empress Dowager first and foremost,
the mother of the Emperor,
the honor-bearer of the Uya Clan,
and then I am the prior emperor's Consort Digne,
and your bosom friend.
Back then you told me that
the prior emperor didn't like pink and blue,
and told me to wear these colors
for the concubine selection.
But in fact, you already knew,
the prior emperor's favorite colors were pink and blue.
You wanted me to enter the harem
only to support the position of your sister,
the Empress Xiaoyiren, in the harem.
If Empress Xiaoyiren wasn't childless,
you would not have supported my son for the throne.
You wrote off my life.
Now,
it's my turn to write off yours.
Only your death ...
can bring peace
to my son.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
It's His Lordship's flute again.
Is it?
Only His Lordship's flute has
such an affecting tone.
I wonder how late he will play until tonight.
My Lady, listen.
Can you still hear the sound of the flute?
Yes, I can.
How pitiable.
It's raining outside.
I'm afraid he'll be soaked.
Mistress.
The past is the past.
If you continue to wallow in self-pity,
not only is it torturing yourself,
but also His Lordship.
All these days, I've been able to see with my own eyes
that His Lordship is full of love and devotion
and is someone you could entrust your whole life to.
Allow me to say something I shouldn't.
Who knows what the future will look like?
"When your eyebrows catch fire, you
should only attend to what's right in front of you."
Only attend to...
What's right in front of me?
Precisely.
We always say "tomorrow".
But who knows what tomorrow will bring?
You should follow today's heart.
Do what makes you happy.
The future is not worth mistreating yourself today.
My Lady, your umbrella.
My Lady has finally stepped outside.
Yes.
She was going to take that step sooner or later.
The earlier she takes that step,
the earlier they will be happy together.
Huan'er.
Is that you?
It's me.
I'm here.
You shouldn't have come out in the rain.
Do you not care for your health?
You're the one who is neglecting your
health, playing the flute in this torrential rain.
But you are scared of lightning and thunder.
With you here, I'm no longer afraid.
Say that again.
Huan'er, when did you...
start to feel this way about me?
Perhaps at the Cooling Terrace.
Perhaps next to the river.
Perhaps even earlier.
Every time I needed you the most,
you were always right next to me.
Did you know?
If you hadn't told me,
I wouldn't have known how you
felt about me all these years.
“Like the rock that turns into jade; Like the
pine tree that thrives through the seasons.”
“The beauty in this man
is unrepeated under Heaven.”
That is how I feel about you.
Huan'er, in my heart,
you are my world, my heaven and earth.
Without you, all the wealth and riches,
they are but emptiness to me.
As long as I have you,
no matter what I have lost before,
it has been worth it.
I am a discarded woman,
and daughter of an exiled official.
I've been banished to practice Buddhism,
and have given birth to a daughter.
But you ...
You have countless high-born
ladies to choose from.
You really don’t have to be with an outcast like me...
Huan'er, you must believe
you are the best in my heart.
This kind of hand-holding is called
"a heart-joining lock".
A couple who hold hands like this
won't be separated till death.
Huan'er, I hope I'm not dreaming.
Let us never separate.
I feel like it is a dream.
Don't wake me up from this dream.
This is not a dream.
This is what we will have every day from now.
Huan'er, do you know?
How happy I am to have you?
I want to tell my mother right now,
"Your son ..."
"got the person"
"he wanted most in this world."
What a coincidence!
Your Lordship came together
with Mistress Mochou.
Where is my mother?
Her Venerable Highness just finished
chanting scripture and is having some tea.
Mother, mother.
Yunli.
Let’s extend our regards to my mother first.
Peace to Your Venerable Highness.
Peace to you, mother.
What's the matter today?
Making such a formal greeting.
Come.
Ah!
Great! Great!
You two are finally together.
I thank Your Venerable Highness.
It sounds like Your Venerable Highness
already knew that he and I...
I didn't say anything.
Yunli really didn't tell me anything.
I have known since the day when you played the zither and flute together.
Did you think that I was too old to see it?
When two hearts are connected in love,
they are linked as heaven and earth by the "divine rhino's horn".
Come here, my dear.
On that day,
it had just crossed my mind ever so slightly.
I never thought that you and I
have a shared fate so deep.
Sit down, my dear.
Silly boy, why didn't you tell me earlier.
You put me through a lot
by hiding this from me.
This matter just took a favorable turn.
It was only settled yesterday.
That is why I hurried here with Huan'er
to pay our respects.
Huan'er, I brought you to see my mother
because I wanted you to know
that this is not my ephemeral affection.
I hope to hold your hand and grow old with you.
What Yunli said
shows that his affection for you
has been long in the making.
You have finally made it here together.
"Persevere until the clouds have parted,
you can now see the bright moon."
I feel so delighted.
I was worried that
Your Venerable Highness might dislike me.
I understand your worries.
But the past has become the past.
Since the founding of the Great Qing,
I've never heard of a banished
concubine returning to the palace.
Rather than dying of old age outside,
why not find a way to live the life
you want to live?
In the hundred years of life,
how many days are there
when you can satisfy your wishes?
It's a good day today.
Endless Longing and Eternal Promise
are finally together.
They didn't fail to commit to each other.
Mutual and wholehearted love is a rare treasure.
Treasure your happiness.
I will always remember
Your Venerable Highness's words.
Your Majesty, please take a cup of ginseng tea.
How is the Empress Dowager?
Still not very well.
The imperial doctor said Her Majesty
is plagued with uneasy dreams
because stagnant qi has filled the five organs.
Is Your Majesty going to visit Her Majesty?
Her illness comes from her heart.
Even the imperial doctors can't cure it.
What help would my visit be？
It's been a long time since Your Majesty
last visited Her Majesty.
If Your Majesty goes to see her,
It might ease Her Majesty's mind and help her recover.
She is so seriously ill ...
I would have never expected it.
Her illness was caused by me.
She might even hate me.
What could I do to help if I visit?
Your Majesty…
Enough.
I'll go to the Palace of Prolonging
Happiness to see Concubine An.
Yes.
Silly girl.
Ever since I fell ill,
you've been staying here as if
it was your own palace.
It's my great honor to serve Your Majesty.
The emperor might not even harbor
such filial piety as you do.
In fact, where is the emperor?
Bamboo, tell me.
His Majesty is busy arranging
Longkodo's posthumous affairs,
and purging his supporters.
Very well.
He wants to be a good emperor.
I should be glad.
So I can't blame him for not paying his respects.
I should blame myself for falling ill.
Your Majesty,
why do you sound so sad?
I'm not sad.
I'm happy for the emperor.
My child, you're now the only one
staying by my side taking care of me all the time.
Bamboo, announce my decree.
Noble Lady Vertu is promoted to Concubine Vertu.
Yes.
I serve Your Majesty not for titles or ranks.
I know.
It's your filial duty that I wish to reward you for.
Without you serving here all the time,
the emperor would have been
accused of filial impiety by the people.
Yes.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty has been quite bothered these days.
I know I am incapable of
easing Your Majesty's worries.
Coming here has already made me feel better.
Being able to soothe Your Majesty makes
me feel that my humble being is of some use.
You should not look down upon yourself.
You are the most modest and mild
among all the concubines.
I feel comfortable with you.
I made a new incense.
It's the most effective at calming the mind.
I have already lighted it.
How does Your Majesty like it?
Gentle yet sweet, just like you.
Why did you come so early?
I rode back to the Cooling Terrace early this morning,
and saw that the first magnolia tree has blossomed.
So I brought some for you.
We meet where full blossoms envelop the mountain.
Have you eaten yet?
I was in a hurry to come see you.
I'm not hungry at all.
You talk so sweetly as if
your lips were smeared with honey.
Has something happened in the palace?
Long Keduo died while in confinement.
The Empress Dowager is gravely ill.
"Boiling the hound after it kills the cunning hare."
This is a common tactic of His Majesty.
You speak of him today like he's nobody to you.
He is of no concern to me.
How coincidental, I was just feeling like painting.
You've had set everything up.
Can I draw you?
What kind of painter is like this?
You're drawing my portrait without
even looking at me.
How can it resemble me?
Come and look for yourself.
Nicely done.
Although I did not look at you,
your visage was already carved into my mind.
So why would I not be able to paint it?
You are talking nonsense.
If I do this here...
It looks even more like me now.
You're here.
I came at a bad time.
No matter.
Yunli... is not an outsider.
Yunli?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.